Hannibal 지난 이야기
Previously on Hannibal...
이제는 지켜볼
여유가 생긴겁니까?
So is it me or is it becoming
easier for you to look?
저를 드러낼순 있지만
사고가 닫히질 않아요
I can make myself look, but
the thinking is shutting down.
양립될 수 있는,
그런 방식이 아냐
The way that I am isn't
compatible with the way that...
이건 내 방식이야
The way I am.
- 어딘지 아시겠습니까, 그레이엄
- 아뇨
- Do you know where you are, Mr. Graham?
- No.
제 여동생도 잘려진
사슴 머리에 얹혔죠
My sister was impaled
on a severed stag head,
배가 갈린채 말이에요
cut down the middle.
내가 도와주마
시체를 숨기자꾸나
I can help you. We can hide the body.
에비게일만이 유일하게
진실을 알고 있을겁니다
Abigail Hobbs may be the only
person who knows the truth.
아직은 너무 빨라요, 잭
You can't ask her right now, Jack.
집에 가고싶어요
I want to go home.
가장 골치아픈 퍼즐이군요
World's sickest jigsaw puzzle.
그런데 귀퉁이가 어딜까?
Yeah, but where are the corners?
뭐라구요?
What?
퍼즐은 귀퉁이에서
시작한다고들 하잖아
My mom always said, start
a jigsaw with the corners.
머리가 귀퉁이겠죠?
Uh, the heads are the corners, I guess?
그러기엔 너무 많아요
We've got too many corners.
무덤만해도 일곱개나 되요
Seven graves. Way too many heads.
꼭대기쪽만 최근
희생자로 보이는군요
The headpiece appears to
be the only recent victim.
나머지는 몇년에서
수십년까지 됐구요
The others are years, even decades, old.
시체 일곱구가
And we know that seven
여기 묻혀있습니다
of the bodies were buried out here.
어디에 누가 묻혔는지는
묻은 사람만 알겠군요
Whoever dug them up knew
exactly where they were buried.
한 번으로는
부족했을까요
I guess it wasn't enough
for him to kill them once;
다시 찾와서 희생자들을
훼손했으니 말입니다
he had to come back and defile his victims.
훼손같지는 않아요, 잭
These graves weren't desecrated, Jack;
노출시킨거에요
they were exposed.
자, 모두 갑시다
현장들 정리하고!
Ok, everybody, let's go,
let's clear the scene!
전 신중하게 계획했죠
I planned this moment,
이 순간, 이 기념비를...
this monument, with precision.
날 재료를 미리
수집해두었다가
Collected all my raw materials in advance.
몸통을 조심스럽게 쌓아갔죠
I position the bodies carefully,
적절한 위치에 맞게 말이죠
according each its rightful place.
조각의 평화도 해체됐군요
Peace in the pieces disassembled.
제 마지막 희생자는
My latest victim
끝까지 살려뒀어요
I save for last.
일하는걸 그에게
보여주고 싶었군요
I want him to watch me work.
제 디자인을
알아줬으면 한거죠
I want him to know my design.
제 이력서(resume)일까요?
This is my r?um?
이건 제 걸작이자
This is my body of work.
제 유산이죠
This is my legacy.
윌, 올줄 몰랐는데요
Will. I wasn't expecting you.
어떻게 온건지 모르겠군요
I don't know how I got here.
차가 밖에 있던데
운전해온거 아닙니까?
Your car is outside, so we know you drove.
웨스트 버지니아주
그래프톤 해변가에 있었어요
Well, I was on a beach
in Grafton, West Virginia.
눈 한번 깜박였을 뿐인데...
I blinked, and then I... I was
대기실에서 깨버린거에요
자고있던게 아니라면...
waking up in your waiting
room, except I wasn't asleep!
거긴 세시간 반 거리인데
시간 감각도 둔해졌군요
Grafton, West Virginia, is three-and-a-half
hours from here. You lost time.
- 뭔가 잘못된거에요
- 고립되어 있군요, 윌
- Th... there is something wrong with me.
- You're disassociating, Will.
반복된 학대를 견뎌내는
필사적인 생존 원리죠
It's a desperate survival mechanism for
a psyche that endures repeated abuse.
- 아뇨, 아뇨. 학대라니요!
- 공감 장애가 있잖습니까
- No, no, I'm not abused!
- You have an empathy disorder.
- 압도당하는 느낌 말이에요
- 알아요, 알아요, 압니다
- What you feel is overwhelming you.
- I know, I know, I know.
무시하고 싶겠죠
그게 제가 말씀드리는
Yet you choose to ignore
it. That's the abuse
- 학대인 겁니다
- 그만두길 바라는겁니까?
- I'm referring to.
- What, do you want me to quit?
잭은 그만둘 기회를 줬지만
받아들이지 않았죠, 왜죠?
Well, Jack Crawford gave you a chance
to quit, and you didn't take it. Why?
음...
Um...
전 생명을 구해요
I save lives.
- 기분이 좋아지겠군요
- 쉽게 말해서 그렇죠
- And that feels good.
- Generally speaking, yeah.
당신 삶은 어떻습니까?
What about your life?
전 친구잖아요, 윌
I'm your friend, Will.
그 사람들은 제 관심 밖이니
제가 신경쓰는건 당신뿐이죠
I don't care about the lives
you save; I care about your life,
당신은 현실과
동떨어져 있어요
and your life is separating from reality.
제겐 몽유병이 있어요
I've been sleepwalking.
환각도 보이구요
I'm experiencing hallucinations.
- 뇌 스캔이라도 해봐야겠어요
- 윌
- Maybe I should get a brain scan.
- Will.
해답을 찾으러 잘못된
귀퉁이를 보진 마십시요
Stop looking in the wrong
corner for an answer to this.
당신이 혼자 남았을땐
You were at the crime scene
범죄 현장이었겠죠
말씀해보세요
when you disassociated. Tell me about it.
시체로 쌓아올린
토템 폴이 있었어요
It was a totem pole of bodies.
어떤 문화권에선 범죄와
죄책감을 드러내곤 하죠
In some cultures, crimes
and guilt are made manifest
모든 사람이 지켜보고
수치심을 느끼도록 말이죠
so that everyone can see
them and see their shame.
No, this isn't shame;
자축이에요. 그는 업적을
기념하고 있었으니까요
this is celebration. He's
marking his achievements.
그 업적을 지켜보고 있노라니
And faced with this killer's achievements,
도피하고도 싶었겠죠
시간 개념도 잃었을테구요
your mind needed to
escape, and you lost time.
네
Yes.
걱정이군요, 윌
I'm worried about you, Will.
당신은 살인범과 전적으로
공감대를 형성하고 있어요
You empathize so completely
with the killers Jack Crawford
헤어나지 못할 정도로 말이죠
has your mind wrapped around
that you lose yourself to them.
다치기라도 하면 어쩌려구요
What if you lose time and hurt yourself?
가까운 사람은요?
Or someone else?
깨어났을때 스스로 만들어낸
토템을 보지 않았으면 합니다
I don't want you to wake up and
see a totem of your own making.
한글자막 by 클라투
매일 깨어나면
Every day, I wake up, and...
아빠 목소리가 들려요
I hear my dad's voice.
침대옆에 무릎을 꿇고 계시죠
Like he was kneeling next to my bed.
제게 속삭이세요
He whispers what he told me.
여자애들을 죽였다구요
He told me he killed girls.
한 명, 또 한 명
Again and again.
그래서 절 죽일
필요가 없었던거죠
So he wouldn't have to kill me.
아직 살아계셔서
물어볼수 있다면...
I wish he was still alive
so I could ask him...
제가 어떻게 했던건지
what did I make him feel?
제게 문제가 뭐였길래
What was so wrong with me
- 절 죽이려고 하셨는지...
- 그랬어야 했지
- that he wanted to kill...
- He should have.
널 죽였어야 했어
He should have killed you.
- 그래야 내가 죽지 않았을테니까
- So he wouldn't have killed me.
그래야 내가 죽지 않았을테니까
So he wouldn't have killed me.
- 그래야 내가 죽지 않았을테니까
- So he wouldn't have killed me.
널 죽였어야 했어
He should have killed you.
그래야 내가 죽지 않았을테니까
So that you wouldn't have killed me.
오셨군요
Hey.
어제는 죄송했습니다
I'm sorry about yesterday.
무슨 말씀입니까?
Sorry about what?
제 정신이 아니어서요
I... I wasn't feeling like myself.
제 정신이 아니었다...
Well, not feeling like yourself,
늘 그런편 아닙니까?
that's kind of what you do, isn't it?
그런 셈이죠
I suppose so.
네, 알겠습니다
Yeah. Ok.
제가 멀쩡해 보이십니까?
So, I seemed fine to you?
하실 말씀이라도 있습니까?
Is there something you want to tell me?
음, 아뇨, 아뇨
Uh, no. No, no.
그럼 말하기 싫은
뭔가가 있겠군요
Well, clearly there's something
that you don't want to tell me.
어젠 제가 약간 정신을
잃어서, 그게 전부에요
I... I guess I just got a
little lost yesterday, is all.
오늘은 좀 어떻습니까
And where are you today?
그건 제가 알아서 하죠
It got to me.
그 시체들도 그렇구요
All those bodies got to me, and, uh,
그래도 예전보다는
분명히 확실해졌군요
I thought it was a little more
obvious than... than it was.
문제가 있다면 제게
말씀하셔야 할겁니다
If there's a problem, you need to tell me.
그런겁니까, 윌?
Is there a problem, Will?
괜찮습니다
Everything's fine.
좋습니다
All right.
그래요
부모님 집이 팔렸대요
They sold my parents' house.
사람 죽어나간 집은
큰 돈이 안되더군요
Murder houses don't fetch big
money in today's real estate market.
네게 떨어지는건 없겠구나
Not that you'll get any of it.
피해자 가족들이 범죄에 의한
사망으로 소송을 진행중이니까
The families of your father's
victims filed wrongful death suits.
- 범죄에 의한 사망이요?
- 그 말은 피해자 가족들이
- Wrongful death?
- That means that they get
동전 한 푼까지 모두
갖게 된다는 뜻이지
everything, Abigail. Every penny.
여기 네가 갖고
있는게 전부일거야
What you have here is all you have.
그딴 돈은 모두 줘버려요
Let them take all his money.
전 필요없으니까
I don't want any of it.
스스로 벌수도 있어
You can make your own money.
전 얼마나 받게 되죠?
How much would I get
저와 제 아빠에 대해서
if you wrote a book about me?
책을 쓰시면 말이에요
About my dad?
꽤 되겠지
Plenty.
아직도 유효한가요?
Do you still want to tell my story?
네 이야기를 해준다면
I think you need to tell your own story,
내가 널 도와줄 수 있지
but I am the one to help you tell it.
네 아빠에 대해 나보다
많이 아는 사람은 없으니까
No one knows more about what
your father did than I do.
- 윌 그레이엄은요?
- 그는...
- Not even Will Graham?
- Will Graham is
이야기의 일부지,
도와줄 사람은 아니란다
part of the story you tell, Abigail,
not the person to help you tell it.
제가 아버지를 느끼게
한다면서 피하더군요
He avoids me because I make
him feel like my father.
아버지처럼 느껴진다면
범인처럼 느껴지겠지
Feeling like your father
makes him feel like a killer.
사람들은 제가
공범이라고 생각해요
People think I helped
my dad kill those girls.
네가 사람들의 생각을
바꿀 수 있어
Well, you can change what people think.
우리가 함께 바꿀수 있지
We can change that together.
모든 사람들이
진실을 알게될거야
Everyone will know the truth.
좋아요
Ok.
제 이야기를 말해보죠
Let's tell my story.
시체는 몇 구죠?
How many bodies?
전부 17구에요
We got 17 in total.
가장 싱싱한 시체를 만나보시죠
Meet our freshest one,
조엘 서머스
Joel Summers.
40세에,
Forty years old,
테네시주 녹스빌에서
핸드폰 가게를 운영중이죠
runs a cell phone store
in Knoxville, Tennessee.
아니, 운영했었죠
3일동안 실종됐으니까요
Or did. Been missing for three days.
단번에 심장까지 찔렸어요
Single stab wound to the heart.
나머진 사후에 생긴거에요
골절, 대퇴부 및 어깨 탈구...
Other injuries were post mortem...
broken bones, dislocated hips, shoulders.
특별한 존재였겠군요
He was special to him somehow.
존경의 자리에 앉힌거에요
He held a place of honor.
현장의 표식없는 무덤에서도
7구가 나왔구요
Seven bodies from unmarked
graves found at the crime scene.
묻혀있던 시체와
분묘지가 일치합니다
Earth from the body parts
matches the gravesites.
둔기에 의한 외상, 자상에 교살
모두 범죄에 의한 사망이에요
Blunt force trauma, stabbings,
strangulations. Wrongful deaths.
웨스트버지니아 전역에서
There are at least eight other bodies
도굴된 묘지는 적어도
8구 이상이에요
that are recent grave robbings
from all across West Virginia.
범죄 기록도 없고
모두 사고사에요
No crimes attributed to any
of them. Accidental deaths.
모두 살해된거군요
They're all murders.
앤서니 램, 28세
Anthony Lamb, 28,
1986년, 차량사고로 즉사
fatal car wreck, 1986.
프란체스카 부르댕, 42세
Francesca Bourdain, 42,
1994년, 약물에 의한 자살
suicide, pills, 1994.
애드리안 팩햄, 60세
Adrian Packham, 60,
2001년, 혈전증으로 사망
massive coronary, 2001.
피터 맥기, 25세
Peter McGee, 25,
2006년, 일산화탄소
중독으로 사망
carbon monoxide poisoning
in his home, 2006.
해변에 묻혀있던 7구는
아직 확인되지 않았군요
And seven as-yet unidentified
bodies buried on a beach.
모두 사인은 다르지만
Every death is different,
뭔가 특별하게끔
만들어진 겁니다
made to look like something else.
어떤 가학이나
고문의 흔적도 없죠
No sadism, no torture.
범인에게 살인 방법은
단순한 사실보다
The method of these murders
was less important to the killer
덜 중요했을겁니다
than the simple fact...
단순히 죽었다는것
that these people die.
조엘 서머스,
Joel Summers,
심장까지 단번에 찔렸습니다
killed with a single stab to the heart.
남달리 과시하면서
Presented with great ostentation
이전 희생자들의
꼭대기에 올려진겁니다
atop a display of all the previous victims.
살인범의 디자인은 마치
유령처럼 간과된겁니다
This killer's design was to
remain unnoticed, a ghost.
그를 흥분시키고 있는거죠
That is what excited him.
지금까지도...
Until now.
어째서...
Why...
드러내게 됐을까요?
is he coming out into the light?
윌?
Will?
리허설 방해하고
싶지는 않지만...
I don't want to interrupt
if you're rehearsing, or...
음... 아... 아니
괜찮아. 괜찮아
Uh... n... no, no, no. It's ok, it's ok.
여기 꽤 분위기 있는데?
Very moody in here.
음... 온통 나때문인가
Uh... well, that's me all over.
이리 와봐
Come on in.
키스하려고 하진 않을테니까
I promise I won't try to kiss you again.
이제 자기 충고 정도는
무시하게 됐군
Unless you've stopped
taking your own advice.
스스로 치료하는 의사는
환자에게 바보로 보이겠지
A doctor who treats herself
has a fool for a patient.
그날 혼자 남겨두는게 아니었어
I regretted leaving your
house the other night.
후회하는거야?
Regretted?
더이상 후회하지
않겠다는거야,
Implying that you're no longer regretting,
아니면 아직도
후회중이라는거야
or are you still in a state of regret?
중간에 걸쳐있다고 봐야겠지
I'm crisscrossing the state line.
지금은 어느쪽이지?
What side of the line you on now?
한 쪽 발을 양쪽에
붙이고 있었으니까
I've got one foot firmly
planted on both sides.
날 혼란시키려는거야?
Are you telling me that to confuse me?
내 느낌에 대해서
솔직하게 말하는거야
No, I'm telling you that to
be honest about how I feel.
오해하게 만들기도 싫지만,
거짓말도 하기 싫으니까
I don't want to mislead you, but
I don't want to lie to you either.
그럼 나도
거짓말하진 않을거야
I won't lie if you don't.
내게도 감정은 있어, 윌
I have feelings for you, Will.
하지만 우리 사귈수는 없어
But I can't just have an affair with you.
그건...
It would be...
무모하니까
reckless.
왜?
Why?
어째서지?
직업적 호기심때문은 아니잖아
And it is not because you
have a professional curiosity
그래
- about me.
- No.
지금은 너무 불안정해
It's because I think you're unstable.
변화가 있기전까지
친구로 남을수밖에 없어
And until that changes,
I can only be your friend.
거짓말은 아니니 고맙군
Thank you for not lying.
아직도 그런거야?
Do you feel unstable?
Mm.
안좋은 생각이라고 말한건
I'm trying to be understated
그나마 줄여서 말한거란다
when I say that this is a bad idea.
프레디 라운즈는 위험하지
Freddie Lounds is dangerous.
아저씨들 이야기도
She said she wanted me
to write about you guys
책에 쓰겠다고 하던데요
in the book.
우리 프라이버시가
모두 사라지겠구나
You would be forfeiting
your privacy and ours.
이건... 모든게
바뀌게 될거야
This... this... well,
all of this will change.
지금 기분은 모르겠지만
오래 가지 않을테고
Whatever you're feeling
now, that won't last.
상황은 변하니까
Things change.
나도 상황이 바뀌겠지
Things are changing for me too.
난 내 삶에서 뭐가 중요하고
I'm doing some accounting
뭐가 그렇지않은지
설명하는거란다
of what's important in
my life and what isn't.
넌 중요하단다, 애비게일
You are important, Abigail.
제 아빠를 죽 이셨다고해서
대신하실 필요는 없어요
Just because you killed my dad
doesn't mean you get to be him.
애비게일, 우린 끔찍한
Abigail, we've been through
사고를 겪었어. 너보다
충격이 큰 사람은 없겠지
a traumatic event, and
no one more traumatized
하지만 함께 헤쳐나가야지
than you, Abigail, but we
went through it together.
네가 쓰는건
우리 모두의 일이야
What you write, you write about all of us.
허락받을 일인가요?
I don't need your permission.
허락이 필요한건 아니지
다만 의미를 부여했으면 했지만
And you don't need our approval,
but I hope it would mean something.
사람들이 뭐라는지 알아요
I know what people think I did.
그들이 틀렸어요
They're wrong.
제가 사람들이 틀렸다고
이야기하면 왜 안되죠?
Why can't I tell everybody
that they're wrong?
넌 사과할게 없어
You have nothing to apologize for.
하지만
Yet.
네가 문을 연다면
But if you open this door, Abigail,
다가올 일을
통제하지 못할거다
you won't control what comes through.
준비가 됐니?
Are you ready for that?
그래프톤에서의 전시는
이유가 있었을거에요
The display was built
in Grafton for a reason.
토템 폴은 특별한
사건을 기념하죠
Totem poles commemorate special events.
인생의 이야기를 들려주죠
They tell the story of a life.
조엘 서머스가 마지막이라면
이 하단 쪽 시체는
If Joel Summers is his
finale, then this lowest body
살인범의 시작이었겠죠
on the pole will be our killer's beginning.
처음이라...
His first.
플레쳐 마샬
Fletcher Marshall.
1973년, 그래프톤에서
맞아 죽었어요
Murdered in 1973. Beaten
to death right in Grafton.
무덤이 파헤쳐진건
5년 전이구요
His grave was robbed five days ago.
- 용의자도 없구요?
- 아직까지는요
- No one convicted of killing him?
- Not yet.
40년을 건너 뛰었군요
So our guy got away with it 40 years ago.
아직도 진행중이죠
So he kept on going.
연관성이 있을거에요
There will be a connection between
조엘 서머스와
Joel Summers
플레쳐 마샬
and Fletcher Marshall.
윌
Will.
사무실로 오시죠
I need you in my office.
니콜라스 보일이 미네소타에
나타났어요. 사체로 말이죠
Nicholas Boyle turned
up in Minnesota... dead.
숲에서 발견됐는데
잔뜩 얼어있더군요
His body was found in
the woods. He was frozen.
빨리 해동시키긴했는데
1주일전에 죽은건지,
They thawed him out fairly
quickly, but they said
6주전에 죽은건지,
they can't tell if he died a week ago,
사라진 당일에 죽은건지,
알 수가 없다는군요
six weeks ago, or the
night that he disappeared.
사인은요?
How did he die?
칼로 인한 상처가 있더군요
Knife wound. He was gutted.
비행기로 후송시켜 왔습니다
I've had the body flown down here.
애비게일이 확인해줬으면 합니다
I want Abigail Hobbs to identify it for us.
이미 신원파악이 됐을텐데요
You already have a positive ID.
- 애비게일은 아니죠
- 닉 보일의 시체와
- Not from Abigail Hobbs.
- You can't put her in a room
한 방에 둘수는 없죠
아직 악몽에 시달리고 있잖아요
with Nick Boyle's body.
She already has nightmares
왜 그런지 궁금해서요
about him, Jack. I'm curious about why.
아직도 관련이 있다고
보시는겁니까?
You can't think that she has
something to do with this?
난 애비게일이
공통분모라고 봅니다
I think Abigail Hobbs
is the common denominator
그애 아빠나 마리사 슈어,
between her father, Marissa Schuur,
니콜라스 보일, 모두
애비게일로 거슬러 올라가죠
and Nicholas Boyle. They
all go back to Abigail.
제 본능은 애비게일에게
우리가 듣지못한 대답이
My instincts tell me
that Abigail has answers
- 있을거라고 말해주는군요
- 물어보고 싶은게 뭡니까?
that we have not heard.
What are the questions, Jack?
정신병원의 담을 넘었을때
Let's start with where she goes
어디로 갔는지부터
시작해보죠
when she climbs the walls
of the psychiatric facility.
보일을 만나고
있었는지도 모르죠
Maybe she's meeting Nicholas Boyle.
어느 누구도 그들 사이의
일을 알지 못합니다
None of us know what was
really going on between them.
이게 정말
안좋은 생각이란걸
I want to go on record
as saying that this is
녹음이라도 해두고
싶네요, 한니발
a very bad idea. Hannibal?
자기 관심 외에는
Jack has the look of a man
어떤 의견도 관심이
없어 보이는군요
with no interest in
any opinion but his own.
지켜봐 주시죠, 알라나
I want you to observe on this, Alana.
그 애를 시체와 두고싶다면
저도 함께 있겠습니다
If you're putting Abigail in a room
with the body, I want to be there.
미안합니다, 당신의
객관적인 접근은
I'm sorry, Will. I am not very
confident with your ability
확신하지 못하겠군요
to be objective about
Abigail Hobbs right now.
알라나
Alana.
돌이킬수 없는 피해를
노출시킬수도 있어요
He could do Abigail irreparable
damage exposing her to this.
우리 생각보다
강한 아이일지도요
Perhaps she's stronger than we think.
홉스양, 이 자를
봐줬으면 하는데
Miss Hobbs, I want you to look at this man.
너와 블룸 박사,
렉터 박사를
Is this the same person that attacked you,
공격한 자와
동일한 사람이니?
Dr. Bloom, and Dr. Lecter at your home?
맞아요
That's him.
그렇구나
Good.
대답해줬으면 하는
질문이 몇가지 있는데
I just have a few other
questions I'd like you to answer.
공격받은 그날 이후
이 사람을 본적 있니?
Have you seen this man since
the night he attacked you?
덮어주시면 안되요?
Could you cover him up?
대답을 먼저 해주렴
I just need you to
answer the question first.
잠시만요
Please.
아뇨
No.
본적 없어요
I haven't seen him
공격받은... 이후에는요
since h... he attacked me.
이 보일이라는 친구,
This man, Nicholas Boyle,
사냥칼로 찔렸던데
was gutted with a hunting knife.
어떻게 하는지는
알고 있겠지?
You knew how to do that.
- 아빠가 가르쳐 줬을테니까
- 잭, 이런식이면 함께 못해요
- Your father taught you.
- Jack, I won't be party to this.
그럼 가보시죠
Then you can leave.
나름 예의를 차려드렸으니
You're here by invitation,
by courtesy, Dr. Bloom.
방해는 말아주시죠
Please don't interrupt me again.
제가 그랬다고
생각하세요?
You think I did this?
병원에서 탈출하셨을때
Where do you go
어디로 갔었지, 애비게일?
when you escape from the hospital, Abigail?
가끔 시내로 나가거나
숲에도 갔었어요
Sometimes... into the city,
sometimes into the woods,
가끔은 그냥 나갔구요
sometimes just out.
멀어지고 싶었어요
I go get away from... this,
혼자 생각하고...
to be alone where I can...
숨쉴 수 있는 곳으로요
think... breathe.
병원에서 빠져나왔을때
Did you ever meet with Nicholas Boyle
보일을 만나진 않았고?
on one of your little
getaways from the hospital?
공격받은 날 이전에
서로 알고 있었니?
Did the two of you know each other
before the night he attacked you?
네 아버님을 알았을까?
Did he know your father...
아뇨
No.
그의 죽음에 대해선 몰랐겠구나?
And you know nothing about his death?
절 죽이려고 했었죠
I know he tried to kill me.
절 죽이려고 했을때
머릿속에 떠오르던 생각은
And when he was trying to
kill me, all I could think was
이젠 죽게되겠구나
하는 생각뿐이었어죠
that I was gonna die
in that house after all.
하지만...
But I didn't.
전 살아남았죠
I survived.
블룸 박사와...
Dr. Bloom and...
렉터 박사님이 절 살려주셨죠
Dr. Lecter saved my life.
이 자로부터 구해주신거에요
They saved me from him.
그 이후로는 못봤고?
And you haven't seen him since?
제 악몽에서만요
Only in my nightmares.
- 저 애를 믿습니까?
- 애비게일은...
- You believe her?
- I think
충격을 받았어요
묻어버리기 위해
Abigail Hobbs is damaged.
There is something
안간힘을 쓰고있는
뭔가가 있을거에요
she's using every ounce of
that strength to keep buried,
하지만 그게 보일의
사건은 아니라구요, 잭!
but it's not the murder
of Nicholas Boyle, Jack!
- 왜 그리 확신하죠?
- 애비게일에게 갖고 있는
- What makes you so sure?
- Because any reservations
어떤 의구심이라도
한니발에게까진 미치진 못하죠!
I have about Abigail
don't extend to Hannibal!
그 분은 거짓말할
이유가 없잖아요
He has no reason to lie about any of this!
썩어문드러진 괴물 시체가
다시는 돌아오지 못할테니
It can be a comfort to see the
broken, bloated corpse of a monster
그나마 위안이 되는구나
and know it can never come back.
보일은 괴물이 아니었어요
Nick Boyle wasn't a monster.
그럼 넌?
Were you?
가끔은 그렇게 느꼈죠
I sometimes feel like one.
그래서 덮고 싶었던거니?
Is that why you uncovered his body?
이것도 네 책의 일부가
되겠구나, 애비게일?
Would this be a chapter
in your book, Abigail?
닉을 죽인거나, 선생님이
시체를 숨긴건 뺄거에요
No. Neither would killing Nick
or you helping me hide the body.
늘 부록이란건 있잖니
There's always an addendum.
FBI가 이미 했던 질문이에요
이미 대답했고, 전 통과했죠
The FBI already asked their
questions. I answered them. I passed.
잭이 주목하고 있단다
With Jack Crawford's attention.
맞아요. 제가 문을 열었죠
You're right. I opened the door.
모든걸 통제할 순 없어요
하지만 이번만큼은
I can't control what comes
through it, but this time
제가 통제할 수 있었죠
I could control when.
보일을 찾아낸거라면
더이상 두렵지 않아요
I'm not afraid of them
finding Nicholas Boyle anymore.
이미 지난 일이니까요
He's been found.
넌 내 신뢰를 저버렸구나
You betrayed my trust.
너만큼이나 내 삶까지
위태롭게 만들었어
You jeopardized my life
as well as your own.
난 그 이상의 자격이 있지
I deserve more than that.
난 널 믿고싶구나, 애비게일
I need to trust you, Abigail.
그럴수 없다면 어떨까?
What if I can't?
토템 폴 꼭대기의
조엘 서머스는
Joel Summers, the
headpiece of our totem pole,
부모가 돌아가신후
입양된거에요
was adopted after his parents died.
아버지가 누굴까요?
Guess who dad was?
플레쳐 마샬
Fletcher Marshall.
조엘 서머스가
조엘 마샬이군요
Joel Summers is Joel Marshall.
플레쳐 마샬과 조엘 서머스의
DNA 비교를 해봤는데
Uh, we did a DNA comparison between
Fletcher Marshall and Joel Summers.
일치하지는 않더군요
No match.
먀살의 아들이
친자가 아니라구요?
So Marshall's son wasn't his son?
엄마인 엘리노어는
남편이 살해된 4년후
The mom, Eleanor, was killed
in a car accident four years
- 자동차 사고로 사망했어요
- 진짜 사고였을까?
after Fletcher was killed.
Genuine car accident?
살해당한거라면 그녀도
토템 폴 안에 있었겠죠
If she was murdered, she would
have been on the totem pole.
너무 사랑해서 그런 식으로
모욕을 주지 못했다면요?
Well, unless he loved her too
much to disgrace her that way.
마샬의 살인사건에
용의자라도 없었나?
Was anyone ever convicted
for Marshall's murder?
노렌스 웰스가 1973년에 두번,
There was a man named Laurence Wells
심문을 받았지만 구속되진 않았어요
아직도 거기 살고있구요
who was questioned twice in 1973.
Never charged. Still lives in Grafton.
치정 살인이군요
Fletcher Marshall was a crime of passion.
다른 살인과는
다른 점이 있던거에요
It had something that none
of the other murders had.
동기라
Motive.
열려 있소. 들어오시요
It's open. Come in.
무기따윈 없소
I'm unarmed.
기다리고 계셨군요
So you were expecting us.
찾아낼줄 알았으니까
I had faith you'd find me.
왜 그런겁니까, 웰스씨?
And why is that, Mr. Wells?
내가 알려줬을텐데
Because I let you.
마지막 시체는...
That last one was...
마지막이니 다행이라고
생각해둡시다
let's just say it's a good
thing it was the last one.
이제는 싸울 기력도 없소
I don't have the fight in me anymore.
조엘 서머스의 살인을
자백하시는 겁니까?
Are you confessing to the
murder of Joel Summers?
플래쳐 마샬도 더해주시오
And Fletcher Marshall.
거기에 다른 15명까지
And 15 others.
지금쯤이면 다 세어봤겠지만
I assume you've counted 'em up by now.
잡힐까봐 조엘 서머스를
죽이신거로군요
So you killed Joel Summers
just so you'd be caught.
꼭 그렇진 않소
Not just.
조엘 서머스를 죽인건
I killed Joel Summers
의도된 것은 아니었다오
because he was never meant to be.
그럼 다른 사람을
죽인 이유는 뭡니까?
What reason did you
have to kill the others?
내가 죽인 이유야
각각이었지만
I had every reason to kill the others.
그들에겐 사실
이유란건 없었소
They just had no reason to die.
내가 원치 않았다면 그들도
결코 나를 보지 못했을거요
They never saw me coming unless
I wanted them to see me coming.
여자에게 미소짓고
손을 흔들어주면서
I could wave at a lady and smile,
교회에서 노닥거렸을텐데
chew the fat with her in church,
내가 남편을 죽일걸
알면서도 말이요
knowing I killed her husband.
장례식의 엄숙한 의식속엔
There is something beautiful
아름다운 뭔가가 있었지
about that ball of silence at a funeral,
당신 주변의 모든 사람하며,
all those people around you,
당신이 실행할수 있다는걸
알고 있었을테니까
knowing that you made it happen.
당신이 평생 감옥에서 썩게될
Now there's something
beautiful about knowing
아름다운 뭔가가 있겠군요
that you'll spend the rest
of your life in prison.
내가 그리 넉넉해 보이나?
Do I look wealthy to you?
감옥은 은퇴후 근근히 지낼
Prison is gonna be a luxury
내 집 다음으로 내게 사치라오
next to the kind of
retirement home I can afford.
게다가 내가 잊혀질
일도 없을테지
And I certainly won't be forgotten there.
난 나만의...
I'm securing my...
유산을 획득한거니까
I'm securing my legacy.
확실히 기억에
남을만 하겠군요
That's one way to be remembered.
이야기를 들려줄
아이가 없을텐데요
No children to tell your story.
조엘 서머스가
아버지를 기억하던가요?
Did Joel Summers remember his father?
더이상은 아니요
Not anymore.
엘리노어 마샬을 죽이기 전에
Did you have an affair
그녀와 연분이 있었습니까?
with Eleanor Marshall
before you murdered her?
침묵하시니 '예스'라는
뜻으로 알겠습니다
From your silence, I'm
gonna take that as a yes.
- 당신 아들입니다. 조엘 서머스
- 뭐요?
- He was your son. Joel Summers.
- What?
당신이 사랑했던 여자가
You thought the woman you loved was having
당신 아이 대신 플래쳐 마살의
아이를 가졌다고 생각하셨겠죠
Fletcher Marshall's baby when
she should've been having yours,
하지만 헛다리 짚으셨어요
but you got it the wrong way around.
엘리노어는 당신 자식이 아닌
Eleanor chose to raise him
플래쳐 마샬의 자식으로
기를 생각이었던 겁니다
as Fletcher Marshall's
child rather than yours,
그러니 아마도...
so maybe...
당신 속을 들여다 봤을지도요
she saw what's in your heart.
유산을 획득한게 아니라
아예 없애버리셨군요
You didn't secure your legacy,
Mr. Wells; you murdered it.
아버지로 유일하게 하신 일이
In fact, your one act as a father was
아드님을 파멸시킨거군요
to destroy your son.
누군가를 죽인다는게
Killing somebody,
그렇게 기분나쁜건가요?
it feels that bad?
악몽이 두려워요
I'm worried about nightmares.
우리가 도와줄 수 있지
We'll help you with the nightmares.
무반주 첼로 모음곡 제2번
"사라방데" by 바흐
"Sarabande" by Bach playing)
왔군요, 윌
애비게일이 닉 보일을 죽였어요
Abigail Hobbs killed Nick Boyle.
알고 있습니다
Yes, I know.
어떻게 아신거죠?
Tell me why you know.
시체 치우는걸 도왔죠
I helped her dispose of the body.
확실히...
Evidently...
충분치 않군요
not well enough.
잭에게 이야기 했습니까?
Have you told Jack Crawford?
아뇨
No.
왜 그랬죠?
Why not?
사실이 아니길 바랬으니까요
Because I was hoping it wasn't true.
이제 진실을 아셨군요
Well... now you know the truth.
제가요?
Do I?
알고 계신 모든게 사실입니다
결말만 다를뿐이죠
Everything you know about that
night is true, except the end.
니콜라스 보일은 우릴 공격했죠
Nicholas Boyle attacked us.
애비게일의 죄라면
정당방위일뿐이에요
Abigail's only crime was to defend herself,
- 제가 거짓말한겁니다
- 왜죠?
- and I lied about it.
- Why?
아실텐데요
You know why.
잭은 아버지의 죄를 물어
그녀를 매달테고
Because Jack Crawford would hang her
그럼 세상은 그녀를
불태워 굴복시키겠죠
for what her father's done,
and the world would burn Abigail
그래야 이야깃거리가 될테니까
in his place. That would be the story.
프레디 라운즈의 속셈도 그렇죠
That would be what Freddie Lounds writes.
애비게일은 살인자에,
Abigail is no more a killer than you are
당신은 그애 아버지를 쐈고
전 토바이어스의 죽음에 책임이 있겠죠
for shooting her father, or I
am for the death of Tobias Budge.
- 우리가 결정할 일이 아닙니다
- 그럼 누구죠?
- It isn't our place to decide.
- If not ours, then whose?
우리보다 그 애를 더
잘 아는 사람이 있을까요?
Who knows Abigail better than you and I?
그녀가 안고 있는 부담감은?
Or the burden she bears?
이제 우리가
그애 아버지입니다
We are her fathers now.
우리가 제이콥 홉스보다
그녀를 잘 돌봐야합니다
We have to serve her better
than Garret Jacob Hobbs.
잭에게 가시겠다면
그 애의 미래를 죽이는거죠
If you go to Jack, then
you murder Abigail's future.
변호사를 불러둘까요, 윌?
Do I need to call my lawyer, Will?
누구에게도 말하면 안됩니다
We can tell no one.
지금 하는 일이
옳은 일입니다
What we are doing here is the right thing.
때가 된다면, 이번 일은
묻어둘 이야기가 되겠죠
In time, this will be the only
story any of us cares to tell.
어쩌죠, 라운즈씨
I feel terrible Ms. Lounds.
채식주의자일거란
생각은 못했는데 말이죠
Never entered my head
you might be a vegetarian.
전적으로 제 실수군요
A lapse on my behalf.
철저한 조사는
이익을 가져다주죠
Research always delivers benefits.
좋은 이야기가 묻히더라도
어쨌든 펴내야 되는거겠죠
If it contradicts a good
story, hell, publish it anyway.
정신이상이라고 해서
아직도 화가 나신건가요?
Are you still angry I called you insane?
명예훼손 부분은
결백한데요, 그레이엄
The libel laws are clear, Mr. Graham.
은유는 늘
모호한 법이니까요
Insinuation is such a grey area.
정신이상은 검거나 흰
문제가 아니잖아요?
Insane isn't really black or white, is it?
우린 각자 병적인 문제가 있죠
We're all pathological in our own ways.
당신은 가장 어울리는
진실의 단면을 선택해서는
You choose the version of
the truth that suits you best
병적으로 추구하고 계시죠
and pursue it pathologically.
누구나 자신만의 진실로
판단을 내리죠
Everybody decides their
own versions of the truth.
제가 여기 온건 애비게일의
진실을 말하고 싶어서에요
I'm here because I want to tell
Abigail's version of the truth.
아무렴요
See that you do.
전 숨길게 없어요
I don't have anything to hide.
누구나 숨길게 있지
Everyone has something to hide,
하지만 네가 원치않으면
나도 말하지 않을테니까
but I won't tell anything
you don't want me to.
우리 걱정을
이해했으면 합니다
You must understand our concerns.
걱정되서 그러는거니까요
We care about Abigail.
다 그녀를
보호하려는 생각이죠
Our only thought is to protect her.
이미 다 노출됐어요
Hm. She's already exposed.
지금까지의 침묵은
Her silence until now has
유죄로 간주될뿐이죠
been taken as guilt.
이 책은 그녀의
무고에 관한거에요
This book is about her innocence.
애비게일에게도
미래가 있었으면 해요
I want Abigail to have a future.
그게 우리가
원하는것 일테구요
That's what we all want.
우리 모두 최선의
방법을 원했던겁니다
Well, we all want what's best for Abigail.
지금까지 먹어본 샐러드중
가장 훌륭한데요
This is possibly the finest
salad I've ever eaten in my life.
온갖 고기들로 망쳐진게
아쉽긴 하지만요
Shame to ruin it with all that meat.
윌도 알고있어요, 그렇죠?
Will knows, doesn't he?
보일을 죽인거라면, 그렇지
He knows you killed Nicholas Boyle, yes.
어떻해야 하죠?
What am I gonna do?
비밀은 지켜줄거다
He will keep our secret.
- 어떻게 아세요
- 그렇지않다면...
- You don't know that.
- He will keep it
인생의 오점으로 남을테니까
because otherwise the one good
thing in his life is tainted.
잭에게도 거짓말로 덮어줄거다
And he will lie to Jack Crawford about you
자기 자신에게 그랬던것처럼
just as he has lied to himself.
넌 자유롭단다, 애비게일
You're free, Abigail.
네가 한 일은
아무도 모를테니까
No one will know what you did.
게다가 네가 회피하려는
진실 역시 아무도 모르겠지
And no one will know the
truth you're trying to avoid.
네 스스로 인정할 수
없는게 있지
The one you cannot admit even to yourself.
제가 도왔어요
I helped him.
- 뭐라고?
- 제가 도와드렸다구요
- I can't hear you.
- I helped him.
아버지가 어떤 분인지,
무슨 짓을 하셨는지 알았어요
I knew what my father was. I
knew what he did. I... I knew.
바로 제가...
I was the one who...
여자애들을 만나서
met the girls,
말을 걸었죠
talked to them.
웃고 농담도 했어요
Laughed and joked.
어디 살고 있고,
Found out where they lived,
어디로 가고있는지,
where they were going,
언제 혼자가 되는지
알아냈죠
when they'd be alone.
여자애들은 저와
무척이나 닮았어요
Girls that looked just like me.
제 친구가 될수도 있었는데
They could have been my friends.
아빠한테 안된다고
말하지 못했어요
I couldn't say no to him. I knew...
그애들이 아니면
제가 죽었을테니까요
I knew it was them or me.
언제 말해줄지 궁금했었다
I wondered when you would tell me.
전 괴물이에요
I'm a monster.
아니
No.
괴물이 뭔지는 알고 있다
I know what monsters are.
넌 피해자일뿐이지
You're a victim.
윌과 내가...
And Will and I...
너를 보호해줄거다
we're going to protect you.
앉아도 될까?
Mind if I sit?
아, 그래. 물론이지
Oh, yeah, sure.
고마워
Thanks.
혼자 여행하는건 질색이라
I hate traveling by myself.
난 좋은데
I love it.
- 어디 가니?
- 주말 동안 집에 가보려고
- Where are you going?
- Home for the weekend.
너는?
How about you?
한글자막 by 클라투